You came because of
You came because of
those rumors, right?
those rumors, right?
About us two,
About us two,
I bet everyone in your household
I bet everyone in your household
knows it by now.
knows it by now.
Probably.
Mungkin.
As for who started it,
As for who started it,
it's easy to guess.
it's easy to guess.
Can't be more than three people.
Can't be more than three people.
For a young lady,
For a young lady,
this kind of thing's awkward to handle.
this kind of thing's awkward to handle.
So…
So…
maybe I should step in.
maybe I should step in.
What are you planning to do?
What are you planning to do?
Simple.
Simple.
I'll come propose.
I'll come propose.
No,
No,
that's way too fast!
that's way too fast!
Aren't we still figuring things out?
Aren't we still figuring things out?
Please don't do anything yet.
Please don't do anything yet.
I can handle it myself.
Saya bisa menanganinya sendiri.
Since everyone already knows,
Since everyone already knows,
we might as well
we might as well
make it official.
make it official.
No.
TIDAK.
I still need time to think.
I still need time to think.
Please, I'm begging you.
Please, I'm begging you.
Alright.
Baiklah.
We'll do it your way.
We'll do it your way.
You should head to the palace.
You should head to the palace.
State matters are waiting for you.
State matters are waiting for you.
I'm off then.
I'm off then.
I'll wait for your message.
I'll wait for your message.
Nannies, what are you…
Nannies, what are you…
What are you doing?
Apa yang sedang kamu lakukan?
You little brat,
You little brat,
always running your mouth!
always running your mouth!
Gonna send you somewhere that'll teach you a lesson!
Gonna send you somewhere that'll teach you a lesson!
Hold it. Move!
Hold it. Move!
What's all this?
What's all this?
Miss Qingpu, save me!
Miss Qingpu, save me!
Behave yourself!
Behave yourself!
What a coincidence.
What a coincidence.
I wanted to tie her up too.
I wanted to tie her up too.
How about
How about
you hand her over to me?
you hand her over to me?
Mother!
Mother!
Mother.
Ibu.
I heard everything.
I heard everything.
Sorry for troubling you.
Sorry for troubling you.
Lian!
Lian!
Mother.
Ibu.
Why would you do this?
Why would you do this?
Mother, I was just mad at her.
Mother, I was just mad at her.
Why should she
Why should she
steal my savings
steal my savings
and still expect me
and still expect me
to cover up her scandal?
to cover up her scandal?
Why should I?
Why should I?
Her scandal?
Her scandal?
That's Chen Yanyun!
That's Chen Yanyun!
But didn't you tell me
But didn't you tell me
that Chen Yanyun
that Chen Yanyun
just keeps her as a mistress?
just keeps her as a mistress?
Mistress or not,
Mistress or not,
she's still
she's still
his woman!
his woman!
If Chen Yanyun hears
If Chen Yanyun hears
you've been spreading rumors
you've been spreading rumors
about her and another man,
about her and another man,
he'll never let it slide.
he'll never let it slide.
So what?
Lalu kenapa?
Chen Yanyun may be powerful,
Chen Yanyun may be powerful,
but can he really meddle
but can he really meddle
in our family business?
in our family business?
I'm gonna get back at Gu Jinzhao!
I'm gonna get back at Gu Jinzhao!
So what if she has Chen Yanyun?
So what if she has Chen Yanyun?
I still have Wenxiu,
I still have Wenxiu,
and the Yao family!
and the Yao family!
I'm not scared of her!
I'm not scared of her!
Compared to Chen Yanyun,
Compared to Chen Yanyun,
the Yao family means nothing!
the Yao family means nothing!
If you keep causing trouble outside,
If you keep causing trouble outside,
you'll get your father killed someday
you'll get your father killed someday
and bring disaster to our whole Gu family!
and bring disaster to our whole Gu family!
Please calm down, Mother.
Please calm down, Mother.
Mother,
Ibu,
Lian was really
Lian was really
reckless this time.
reckless this time.
But it's not that serious, is it?
But it's not that serious, is it?
At worst,
At worst,
we apologize in private
we apologize in private
and let it go.
and let it go.
If this really gets exposed,
If this really gets exposed,
even Chen Yanyun
even Chen Yanyun
would lose face.
would lose face.
What do you know?
Apa yang kamu ketahui?
Deyuan's career
Deyuan's career
will be ruined by you sooner or later!
will be ruined by you sooner or later!
Ma'am!
Ma'am!
It's bad!
It's bad!
Tang wasn't sent away and
Tang wasn't sent away and
Ms. Jinzhao got her.
Ms. Jinzhao got her.
Ms. Jinzhao is here!
Ms. Jinzhao is here!
Grandmother, Auntie.
Grandmother, Auntie.
Lian is here too.
Lian is here too.
Seems everyone's here,
Seems everyone's here,
saved me the trouble of going around.
saved me the trouble of going around.
No need for that tone.
No need for that tone.
I know you've been wronged.
I know you've been wronged.
I've heard
I've heard
about the rumors too.
about the rumors too.
Your Auntie has been investigating all day.
Your Auntie has been investigating all day.
We've figured it out now.
We've figured it out now.
It was Tang who spread them.
It was Tang who spread them.
I was just about to send someone
I was just about to send someone
to arrest her.
to arrest her.
We were thinking the same thing.
We were thinking the same thing.
Grandmother, you're truly wise.
Grandmother, you're truly wise.
But I think
But I think
Tang wouldn't have done it
Tang wouldn't have done it
for no reason.
for no reason.
Someone must have ordered her.
Someone must have ordered her.
Right, Tang?
Right, Tang?
Tang,
Tang,
don't you dare talk nonsense.
don't you dare talk nonsense.
if Qingpu hadn't arrived in time,
if Qingpu hadn't arrived in time,
you'd already
Anda sudah
be sent to the estate.
dikirim ke perkebunan.
It was Ms. Lian who told me to do it.
Ibu Lian-lah yang menyuruh saya melakukannya.
She told me to go to Baoxiang Temple!
Dia menyuruhku pergi ke Kuil Baoxiang!
Ms. Lian sent you there
Nyonya Lian yang mengirimmu ke sana.
to pray for a
berdoa untuk
consecrated bracelet,
gelang yang disucikan,
not to spread nonsense here
jangan menyebarkan omong kosong di sini
and ruin her reputation!
dan merusak reputasinya!
Exactly!
Tepat!
I never told you to spread rumors!
Aku tidak pernah menyuruhmu menyebarkan rumor!
Miss,
Merindukan,
it was you who sent me!
Kaulah yang mengirimku!
If you hadn't taught me,
Seandainya kau tidak mengajariku,
how could I have ever said those things?
Bagaimana mungkin aku pernah mengatakan hal-hal itu?
You…
Anda…
Don't you dare twist the truth!
Jangan berani-beraninya kau memutarbalikkan kebenaran!
Mother.
Ibu.
Nanny Su. Yes!
Nama Pengasuh. Ya!
Slap her!
Tampar dia!
Ms. Jinzhao,
Nona Jinzhao,
it really was Ms. Lian who told me to spread rumors
Ternyata memang Bu Lian yang menyuruh saya menyebarkan rumor.
about you and Mr. Wang!
tentang Anda dan Tuan Wang!
And,
Dan,
she specifically sent me to Baoxiang Temple,
Dia secara khusus menyuruhku pergi ke Kuil Baoxiang,
saying I should spread it among the servants
mengatakan bahwa aku harus menyebarkannya di antara para pelayan.
since many noble ladies go there to pray!
karena banyak wanita bangsawan pergi ke sana untuk berdoa!
It was
Itu adalah
all Ms. Lian's order!
Semua pesanan dari Ibu Lian!
I didn't!
Aku tidak!
Grandmother. Enough!
Nenek. Cukup!
Tang
Bau
was originally
awalnya
Lian's personal maid.
Pelayan pribadi Lian.
Since you spread rumors on your own
Karena kamu sendiri yang menyebarkan rumor.
and falsely accused your miss…
dan menuduh Nona Anda secara salah…
Have her flogged 20 times,
Suruh dia dicambuk 20 kali,
then send her to the estate,
lalu kirim dia ke perkebunan itu,
never allow her to return to the capital!
Jangan pernah izinkan dia kembali ke ibu kota!
Grandmother,
Nenek,
Tang deserves punishment,
Tang pantas dihukum,
no matter what it is.
apa pun itu.
But don't forget,
Tapi jangan lupa,
the one behind this is Lian.
Orang di balik semua ini adalah Lian.
Don't show favoritism.
Jangan menunjukkan pilih kasih.
Why are you so anxious?
Mengapa kamu begitu cemas?
Who said I'm protecting Lian?
Siapa bilang aku melindungi Lian?
Lian
Lian
failed to discipline her servants
gagal mendisiplinkan para pelayannya
and let a mistress suffer.
dan biarkan seorang selir menderita.
She must be punished too.
Dia juga harus dihukum.
20 slaps to the palm,
20 tamparan di telapak tangan,
and three days kneeling
dan berlutut selama tiga hari
in the ancestral hall.
di aula leluhur.
Grandmother…
Nenek…
What?
Apa?
That's too light!
Itu terlalu ringan!
Gu Jinzhao, listen up,
Gu Jinzhao, dengarkan.
don't push your luck!
Jangan coba-coba!
Lian knows she was wrong.
Lian tahu dia salah.
Thank you, Mother. We accept the punishment.
Terima kasih, Ibu. Kami menerima hukuman ini.
Let's go. We'll take our punishment!
Ayo pergi. Kami akan menerima hukuman kami!
We know we were wrong!
Kami tahu kami salah!
Nanny Su.
Nama Pengasuh.
Drag that wench out now!
Seret perempuan itu keluar sekarang juga!
Got it. Someone here!
Oke. Ada seseorang di sini!
Drag her out!
Seret dia keluar!
Ma'am!
Bu!
Ma'am, I'm innocent!
Bu, saya tidak bersalah!
Move!
Bergerak!
My lady made me do it all!
Istriku menyuruhku melakukan semuanya!
- I'm innocent! - Move!
- Aku tidak bersalah! - Minggir!
Ma'am!
Bu!
All of you out.
Kalian semua keluar.
Jinzhao, you stay.
Jinzhao, diamlah.
Yes.
Ya.
Qingpu, you go too.
Qingpu, kamu juga ikut.
Grandmother,
Nenek,
what are you trying to do?
Apa yang sedang kamu coba lakukan?
Jinzhao,
Jinzhao,
don't look at me like that.
Jangan menatapku seperti itu.
About this matter,
Mengenai hal ini,
I of course know
Tentu saja aku tahu
it's Lian's fault.
Ini semua kesalahan Lian.
But your auntie
Tapi bibimu
has only one
hanya punya satu
legitimate daughter.
anak perempuan sah.
We can't just throw her out!
Kita tidak bisa begitu saja mengusirnya!
To put it bluntly,
Terus terang saja,
your reputation's already ruined.
Reputasimu sudah hancur.
But if Lian's name
Tapi jika nama Lian
gets ruined too…
ikut rusak juga…
Then our Gu family,
Kemudian keluarga Gu kami,
Hui, Lan,
Hui, Lan,
Jinrong, Jinxian,
Jinrong, Jinxian
what will they do?
Apa yang akan mereka lakukan?
How will they ever marry?
Bagaimana mereka bisa menikah?
How will they live?
Bagaimana mereka akan hidup?
So the top priority now
Jadi prioritas utama sekarang
is not punishment,
bukanlah hukuman,
but how to fix this!
Tapi bagaimana cara memperbaikinya!
Looks like you already have a plan, Grandmother.
Sepertinya Nenek sudah punya rencana.
Don't think
Jangan berpikir
what you did
apa yang kamu lakukan
that night, sneaking off to Cuizhu Residence,
Malam itu, diam-diam pergi ke Kediaman Cuizhu,
went unnoticed.
tidak diperhatikan.
You don't really think
Kamu sebenarnya tidak berpikir
you can marry Chen Yanyun, do you?
Kamu bisa menikahi Chen Yanyun, kan?
You're overthinking it.
Kamu terlalu banyak berpikir.
If Chen Yanyun
Jika Chen Yanyun
truly wanted to marry you,
Aku sangat ingin menikahimu,
why would he
mengapa dia
meet you in secret,
bertemu denganmu secara rahasia,
instead of openly
alih-alih secara terbuka
coming to propose?
Apakah Anda datang untuk melamar?
Clearly,
Jelas sekali,
he only treated you
dia hanya memperlakukanmu
like some woman outside.
seperti wanita di luar.
I know.
Aku tahu.
You don't care about your reputation.
Kamu tidak peduli dengan reputasimu.
But the daughters of the Gu family
Namun putri-putri dari keluarga Gu
cannot become someone's kept woman!
tidak bisa menjadi wanita simpanan seseorang!
So the only way now
Jadi satu-satunya cara sekarang
is for you to marry Wang Zan
adalah agar kamu menikahi Wang Zan
and keep everything peaceful.
dan menjaga agar semuanya tetap damai.
Lian spread rumors about me and Wang Zan.
Lian menyebarkan desas-desus tentang aku dan Wang Zan.
So Grandmother, your solution is
Jadi, Nenek, solusinya adalah...
to marry me off?
untuk menikahkan aku?
Looks like
Sepertinya
you really value Wang Zan.
Anda sangat menghargai Wang Zan.
Marriage has always,
Pernikahan selalu,
since ancient times,
sejak zaman kuno,
been arranged by one's parents.
telah diatur oleh orang tua seseorang.
I'm not here to discuss it with you.
Saya tidak di sini untuk membahasnya dengan Anda.
Neither am I discussing it with you.
Aku juga tidak akan membahasnya denganmu.
I will not marry him.
Aku tidak akan menikah dengannya.
You should give up on this idea.
Sebaiknya kamu lupakan ide ini.
How outrageous!
Sungguh keterlaluan!
Who allowed you
Siapa yang mengizinkanmu?
to speak to your elders like that?
Berbicara kepada orang yang lebih tua seperti itu?
I heard everything
Aku mendengar semuanya
you said to Uncle Deyuan.
Anda mengatakan itu kepada Paman Deyuan.
Aren't you afraid
Apakah kamu tidak takut?
that by forcing me like this,
bahwa dengan memaksa saya seperti ini,
after I marry into the Wang family,
setelah saya menikah dan menjadi anggota keluarga Wang,
I'll reveal everything
Aku akan mengungkapkan semuanya
I shouldn't?
Seharusnya aku tidak?
That is the Minister of Justice's household!
Itu adalah kediaman Menteri Kehakiman!
Do you think
menurut mu
that right now in the Gu family,
bahwa saat ini di keluarga Gu,
no one can do anything to you?
Tidak ada seorang pun yang bisa melakukan apa pun padamu?
Someone here!
Ada seseorang di sini!
Yes!
Ya!
Lock her in the woodshed,
Kurung dia di gudang kayu,
without my order, she's not allowed out!
Tanpa surat perintah saya, dia tidak diizinkan keluar!
Yes!
Ya!
Who would dare!
Siapa yang berani!
Ma'am.
Bu.
Mr. Ji has arrived.
Tuan Ji telah tiba.
And he brought more than ten carts of gifts,
Dan dia membawa lebih dari sepuluh gerobak berisi hadiah,
saying he's here to propose.
mengatakan bahwa dia datang untuk melamar.
He wants
Dia ingin
to marry Ms. Jinzhao.
untuk menikah dengan Nona Jinzhao.
Isn't that just a marriage proposal?
Bukankah itu hanya lamaran pernikahan?
What's the big deal?
Apa masalahnya?
So if someone comes to propose,
Jadi jika seseorang datang untuk melamar,
I can't punish my granddaughter?
Apakah saya tidak bisa menghukum cucu perempuan saya?
Do it.
Lakukanlah.
Ma'am,
Bu,
the Ji family serves the Chen family.
Keluarga Ji melayani keluarga Chen.
Alright.
Baiklah.
Have Mr. Ji wait in the front hall.
Suruh Pak Ji menunggu di aula depan.
I'll go now.
Saya akan pergi sekarang.
Yes.
Ya.
Have Deyuan and Dezhao returned?
Apakah Deyuan dan Dezhao sudah kembali?
Only Master Dezhao is off duty,
Hanya Master Dezhao yang sedang tidak bertugas,
he just got back.
Dia baru saja kembali.
Have him go too. Yes.
Suruh dia ikut juga. Ya.
Go quickly!
Pergi cepat!
You called
Anda menelepon
Mr. Ji here, right?
Pak Ji di sini, kan?
No.
TIDAK.
Then was it Chen Yanyun?
Lalu, apakah itu Chen Yanyun?
Of course not!
Tentu saja tidak!
Miss.
Merindukan.
Mr. Ji actually came to propose to you.
Sebenarnya, Tuan Ji datang untuk melamar Anda.
I don't know what's going on.
Aku tidak tahu apa yang sedang terjadi.
Let's go
Ayo pergi
around back and take a look.
Ke belakang dan lihatlah.
My greetings, Madam,
Salam hormat, Nyonya,
Second Madam, Fourth Master.
Nyonya Kedua, Tuan Keempat.
Mr. Ji,
Tuan Ji,
you want to marry Jinzhao?
Apakah kamu ingin menikahi Jinzhao?
Yes.
Ya.
My Grandmother
Nenekku
personally prepared the betrothal gifts.
menyiapkan sendiri hadiah pertunangan tersebut.
Madam, and Fourth Master, please review.
Nyonya, dan Tuan Keempat, mohon periksa kembali.
2000 taels of gold.
2000 tael emas.
And 50,000 taels of silver?
Dan 50.000 tael perak?
Mother!
Ibu!
Well,
Dengan baik,
we can talk.
Kita bisa bicara.
I've also prepared some small gifts
Saya juga sudah menyiapkan beberapa hadiah kecil.
for all the elders.
untuk semua orang tua.
Please accept them.
Silakan terima.
Madam,
Nyonya,
I got this jade bracelet
Aku mendapatkan gelang giok ini
on a grain transport voyage to Toungoo.
dalam perjalanan pengangkutan biji-bijian ke Toungoo.
Wear it on your wrist,
Kenakan di pergelangan tanganmu,
and it stays warm in winter and cool in summer.
dan tetap hangat di musim dingin dan sejuk di musim panas.
Mr. Ji,
Tuan Ji,
you've spent too much.
Kamu sudah menghabiskan terlalu banyak uang.
Coming from so far
Datang dari tempat yang sangat jauh
must have been hard.
Pasti sulit.
On my word.
Demi kata-kataku.
Ma'am.
Bu.
Attend to Mr. Ji as he washes up,
Bantulah Pak Ji saat beliau mencuci piring,
and,
Dan,
then escort him to the main hall for dinner.
lalu mengantarnya ke aula utama untuk makan malam.
Yes.
Ya.
Thank you, Madam.
Terima kasih, Bu.
Mr. Ji,
Tuan Ji,
please.
Tolong.
What?
Apa?
You dare to come propose,
Kau berani datang melamar,
but doesn't dare see me?
tapi tidak berani menemuiku?
Not like you,
Tidak seperti kamu,
no shame at all,
tidak ada rasa malu sama sekali,
and you don't even protect yourself.
dan kamu bahkan tidak melindungi dirimu sendiri.
You've caused such a scene,
Kamu telah membuat keributan besar,
making Grandmother
membuat Nenek
lose sleep for days.
Sulit tidur berhari-hari.
What?
Apa?
Did maternal grandmother send you?
Apakah nenek dari pihak ibu yang mengirimmu?
No.
TIDAK.
Grandmother didn't mention it.
Nenek tidak menyebutkannya.
I came on my own.
Saya datang sendirian.
I heard those filthy rumors.
Aku mendengar desas-desus kotor itu.
Those are all rumors.
Itu semua hanya rumor.
I know they're rumors.
Saya tahu itu hanya rumor.
But gossip is a deadly weapon.
Namun, gosip adalah senjata yang mematikan.
Even a man can't handle it,
Bahkan seorang pria pun tidak bisa menanganinya,
let alone a young lady like you.
apalagi seorang wanita muda sepertimu.
I just can't stand them
Aku benar-benar tidak tahan dengan mereka.
spreading nonsense and ruining your name.
Menyebarkan omong kosong dan merusak nama baikmu.
But you didn't have to propose!
Tapi kamu tidak perlu melamar!
Proposing is the best solution.
Mengajukan proposal adalah solusi terbaik.
I looked into it.
Saya menyelidikinya.
That Wang Zan
Wang Zan itu
is a known scoundrel.
adalah seorang penjahat terkenal.
Who knows
Siapa tahu?
what trouble he'll cause in the future?
Masalah apa yang akan dia timbulkan di masa depan?
Instead of guarding against rumors,
Alih-alih berjaga-jaga terhadap rumor,
I'd like
Saya ingin
to propose to you now.
untuk melamar Anda sekarang.
If anyone dares trouble you later,
Jika ada yang berani mengganggumu nanti,
I'll have every right
Saya akan memiliki hak penuh.
to deal with them!
untuk menghadapi mereka!
Miss Gu,
Nona Gu,
Mr. Ji arrived in the capital yesterday at noon.
Tuan Ji tiba di ibu kota kemarin siang.
He was supposed to meet guests.
Dia seharusnya bertemu dengan para tamu.
But then he heard
Tapi kemudian dia mendengar
you were being bullied.
Kamu sedang diintimidasi.
He was terribly anxious,
Dia sangat cemas,
canceled all his appointments
membatalkan semua janji temuannya
and immediately went back to Tongzhou to prepare.
dan segera kembali ke Tongzhou untuk bersiap-siap.
Mrs. Ji told him
Nyonya Ji memberitahunya
to wait a few days because of the bad weather.
menunggu beberapa hari karena cuaca buruk.
But he couldn't wait
Tapi dia tidak bisa menunggu.
and came over today anyway.
dan tetap datang hari ini.
Just worried you'd be wronged.
Aku hanya khawatir kamu akan diperlakukan tidak adil.
He didn't even get a sip of water,
Dia bahkan tidak sempat minum seteguk air pun,
and broke out in mouth sores from anxiety.
dan muncul sariawan di mulut akibat kecemasan.
Enough,
Cukup,
you talk too much.
Kamu terlalu banyak bicara.
Come to my courtyard.
Mari datang ke halaman rumahku.
I'll make you lotus seed soup.
Aku akan membuatkanmu sup biji teratai.
How can that be?
Bagaimana mungkin itu terjadi?
I've already proposed,
Aku sudah melamar,
meeting like this is improper enough.
Pertemuan seperti ini sudah cukup tidak pantas.
How could I go to your courtyard?
Bagaimana mungkin saya bisa pergi ke halaman Anda?
You, go back now,
Kamu, kembalilah sekarang juga,
don't worry about anything,
Jangan khawatir tentang apa pun,
just leave it all to me.
Serahkan semuanya padaku.
You all go back.
Kalian semua kembali saja.
Yes.
Ya.
How can you be so willful?
Bagaimana bisa kamu begitu keras kepala?
This… Yao,
Ini… Yao,
I'm really touched
Saya sangat tersentuh.
by what you did.
karena apa yang telah kamu lakukan.
But do you
Tapi apakah kamu
truly like me?
Apakah dia benar-benar seperti aku?
I…
SAYA…
Of course… I like you.
Tentu saja… aku menyukaimu.
Is it
Apakah itu
a brother's love for his sister
kasih sayang seorang kakak laki-laki kepada adik perempuannya
or is it a gentleman's
atau apakah itu milik seorang pria?
admiration for a fair lady?
kekaguman pada seorang wanita cantik?
If I were to marry someone,
Jika aku menikah dengan seseorang,
it would be someone
itu pasti seseorang
who truly loves me
yang benar-benar mencintaiku
and whom I truly love.
dan orang yang sangat saya cintai.
And also,
Dan juga,
a little liking isn't enough.
Sedikit rasa suka saja tidak cukup.
It has to be the kind
Haruslah yang seperti itu
that when I think of it,
bahwa ketika saya memikirkannya,
I can't sleep night after night.
Aku tidak bisa tidur malam demi malam.
I'd keep turning it over in my mind.
Aku akan terus memikirkannya berulang-ulang.
And my face
Dan wajahku
would even flush.
bahkan akan menyiram.
That kind of love.
Cinta seperti itu.
Yao,
Milik mereka,
we grew up together.
Kami tumbuh bersama.
I also hope
Saya juga berharap
you can find someone
Anda bisa menemukan seseorang
you truly love.
Kamu benar-benar mencintainya.
You get married,
Anda menikah,
and she becomes my sister-in-law.
dan dia menjadi saudara ipar saya.
It's getting late,
Sudah larut malam,
go back and rest early.
Kembali dan istirahatlah lebih awal.
I'll have the lotus seed soup
Saya pesan sup biji teratai.
sent to you once it's ready.
Akan dikirimkan kepada Anda setelah siap.
I'll be going now.
Saya permisi dulu.
Can't sleep night after night.
Tidak bisa tidur malam demi malam.
Turning it over in her mind.
Ia memikirkannya berulang kali.
And her face would even flush?
Dan wajahnya bahkan akan memerah?
How is she so clear about it?
Bagaimana dia bisa begitu yakin tentang hal itu?
Sir,
Pak,
something's wrong at Daxin Warehouse.
Ada sesuatu yang tidak beres di Gudang Daxin.
Please take a look.
Silakan lihat.
Bran?
Dedak?
They really went that far!
Mereka benar-benar bertindak sejauh itu!
Go there yourself.
Pergilah ke sana sendiri.
No,
TIDAK,
bring the warehouse manager here,
panggil manajer gudang ke sini,
I'll handle this myself.
Aku akan menangani ini sendiri.
Yes.
Ya.
It used to store rice,
Dulunya tempat ini digunakan untuk menyimpan beras,
but half a month ago it was switched to bran.
Namun, setengah bulan yang lalu, pakan tersebut diganti dengan dedak.
The morning before last they said
Mereka berkata, "Dua pagi yang lalu"
it was to be sent to Pingyang Prefecture for disaster relief.
Paket itu rencananya akan dikirim ke Prefektur Pingyang untuk bantuan bencana.
I also felt something was off.
Saya juga merasa ada sesuatu yang tidak beres.
There was clearly rice in the warehouse,
Jelas sekali ada beras di dalam gudang,
why use bran for relief?
Mengapa menggunakan dedak untuk meredakan nyeri?
But I saw their
Tapi aku melihat mereka
transport documents were all complete,
Dokumen transportasi semuanya lengkap,
so I didn't pursue it.
jadi saya tidak mengejarnya.
Who's in charge
Siapa yang bertanggung jawab?
of this warehouse?
dari gudang ini?
My lord,
Tuanku,
it is Lord Sun Shitao.
Dia adalah Dewa Sun Shitao.
Sun Shitao?
Sun Shitao?
Sir,
Pak,
this Sun Shitao
Sun Shitao ini
hasn't shown up for several days.
Dia belum muncul selama beberapa hari.
Then where did you get orders
Lalu dari mana kamu mendapatkan pesanan itu?
for the grain in and out over the past two days?
untuk biji-bijian yang masuk dan keluar selama dua hari terakhir?
My lord, look.
Tuanku, lihatlah.
Greetings, sir.
Salam, Pak.
Sit.
Duduk.
What happened?
Apa yang telah terjadi?
Why did you have Mr. Jiang
Mengapa Anda membawa Tuan Jiang?
secretly bring me here?
Diam-diam membawaku ke sini?
Don't worry.
Jangan khawatir.
Sit down, let's talk slowly.
Silakan duduk, mari kita bicara perlahan.
No one in the household noticed, right?
Tidak ada seorang pun di rumah yang menyadarinya, kan?
I've got Qingpu watching it.
Aku menyuruh Qingpu untuk menontonnya.
No one will find out.
Tidak akan ada yang tahu.
Come,
Datang,
have some tea,
Minumlah teh,
it'll calm you down.
Ini akan menenangkanmu.
Did something serious happen?
Apakah terjadi sesuatu yang serius?
Otherwise
Jika tidak
you wouldn't have called me here.
Kamu tidak akan memanggilku ke sini.
No matter how urgent it is,
Sekeras apa pun itu,
we shouldn't jump straight into business the moment we meet.
Kita tidak seharusnya langsung membahas bisnis begitu kita bertemu.
How is that
Bagaimana bisa begitu?
any different from being at Grand Secretariat?
Apakah ada perbedaan antara berada di Sekretariat Agung dan di sana?
I heard
saya dengar
Ji Yao proposed to you.
Ji Yao melamar kamu.
I didn't accept.
Saya tidak menerimanya.
By the way,
Omong-omong,
I liked it after
Saya menyukainya setelah itu
trying it last time,
mencoba itu terakhir kali,
so I found some
jadi saya menemukan beberapa
for you to try.
untuk Anda coba.
How is it? Does it taste the same?
Bagaimana rasanya? Apakah rasanya sama?
It's good.
Ini bagus.
Alright, now to business.
Baiklah, sekarang kita mulai.
Pingyang Prefecture is in drought.
Prefektur Pingyang sedang dilanda kekeringan.
The Ministry of Revenue released 200,000 kg of relief grain
Kementerian Pendapatan Negara telah menyalurkan 200.000 kg beras bantuan.
from Daxin Warehouse in Tongzhou.
dari Gudang Daxin di Tongzhou.
But someone interfered
Namun seseorang ikut campur.
and replaced the rice with bran.
dan mengganti beras dengan dedak.
The Ministry of Revenue is under my charge.
Kementerian Pendapatan berada di bawah tanggung jawab saya.
And this
Dan ini
happened right under my nose.
terjadi tepat di depan mata saya.
Clearly,
Jelas sekali,
they want me to take the blame,
Mereka ingin aku yang disalahkan,
but they're also afraid I won't comply.
tetapi mereka juga takut saya tidak akan patuh.
I'm being watched.
Aku sedang diawasi.
That's why
Itulah mengapa
I had to trouble you
Aku harus merepotkanmu
to meet like this.
untuk bertemu seperti ini.
My father
Ayahku
is the Grain Storage Director of the Ministry of Revenue.
adalah Direktur Penyimpanan Gabah di Kementerian Pendapatan.
He oversees Daxin Warehouse.
Dia mengawasi Gudang Daxin.
Could it be… him?
Mungkinkah itu… dia?
He was kept in the dark too.
Dia juga tidak diberi tahu.
Someone forged his official seal.
Seseorang memalsukan stempel resminya.
Who?
Siapa?
Your father's colleague,
Rekan kerja ayahmu,
Sun Shitao.
Sun Shitao.
This man was placed
Pria ini ditempatkan
in the Ministry of Revenue by Wang Xuanfan.
di Kementerian Pendapatan oleh Wang Xuanfan.
He's now gone missing.
Dia sekarang menghilang.
But I've already sent people to find him.
Tapi aku sudah mengirim orang untuk mencarinya.
Wang Xuanfan?
Wang Xuanfan?
Why would he do this?
Mengapa dia melakukan ini?
To bring down Fan Chuan.
Untuk menjatuhkan Fan Chuan.
Zhao Jichang, the Shanxi Provincial Governor,
Zhao Jichang, Gubernur Provinsi Shanxi
is Fan Chuan's brother-in-law.
adalah saudara ipar Fan Chuan.
This man
Pria ini
is extremely greedy
sangat rakus
and colludes with grain merchants.
dan bersekongkol dengan pedagang biji-bijian.
But because of Fan Chuan,
Namun karena Fan Chuan,
no one dares touch him.
Tidak ada yang berani menyentuhnya.
But,
Tetapi,
this disaster relief case is major,
Kasus bantuan bencana ini sangat besar,
so he has to cooperate with the investigation.
jadi dia harus bekerja sama dengan penyelidikan.
And Zhao Jichang's sister,
Dan saudara perempuan Zhao Jichang,
also Fan Chuan's wife,
juga istri Fan Chuan,
is usually very ostentatious.
biasanya sangat mencolok.
She has left behind many handles.
Dia telah meninggalkan banyak nama pengguna.
Once Zhao Jichang falls,
Begitu Zhao Jichang jatuh,
Mrs. Fan
Nyonya Fan
won't escape either.
tidak akan bisa lolos.
By then,
Saat itu,
no matter how Fan Chuan tries to clear his name,
tidak peduli seberapa keras Fan Chuan berusaha membersihkan namanya,
it'll all come crashing down piece by piece.
Semuanya akan runtuh sedikit demi sedikit.
In the end,
Pada akhirnya,
he'll have no choice but to resign as Grand Secretary
Dia tidak punya pilihan lain selain mengundurkan diri sebagai Sekretaris Agung.
and end up in a miserable state.
dan berakhir dalam keadaan yang menyedihkan.
Since
Sejak
it was Wang Xuanfan's move,
Itu adalah langkah Wang Xuanfan,
then the mastermind behind it
lalu dalang di baliknya
must be Fu…
pasti Fu…
Not certain.
Tidak yakin.
He might know,
Dia mungkin tahu,
or he might just
atau mungkin saja dia
be pretending not to.
berpura-pura tidak melakukannya.
No wonder.
Tidak heran.
You knew you were being watched
Kau tahu kau sedang diawasi
but couldn't make a move
tetapi tidak bisa bergerak.
and had to lay low here.
dan harus bersembunyi di sini.
Passing off bran as relief grain,
Menyajikan dedak sebagai makanan penenang,
that is
yaitu
a beheading offense, right?
Kejahatan yang berujung pada pemenggalan kepala, kan?
And if it sparks a riot,
Dan jika hal itu memicu kerusuhan,
then…
Kemudian…
wiping out the whole clan wouldn't be excessive.
Memusnahkan seluruh klan bukanlah hal yang berlebihan.
Then… the relief grain…
Lalu… butiran penolong…
It was shipped out yesterday.
Barang tersebut sudah dikirim kemarin.
Can we still stop it?
Apakah kita masih bisa menghentikannya?
Probably
Mungkin
not.
bukan.
They've set up such a huge trap.
Mereka telah memasang jebakan yang sangat besar.
They won't make a move
Mereka tidak akan bergerak
until the case blows wide open.
sampai kasusnya terungkap sepenuhnya.
What do we do now?
Apa yang harus kita lakukan sekarang?
Don't worry too much.
Jangan terlalu khawatir.
I've got a plan.
Aku punya rencana.
It takes about seven days
Prosesnya memakan waktu sekitar tujuh hari.
from the capital to Pingyang Prefecture.
dari ibu kota ke Prefektur Pingyang.
But news
Namun berita
from Shanxi to the capital
dari Shanxi ke ibu kota
by express courier
melalui kurir ekspres
takes four days
membutuhkan waktu empat hari
at most.
paling banyak.
The grain left yesterday,
Biji-bijian yang tersisa kemarin,
which means
yang berarti
we still have nine days.
Kita masih punya sembilan hari lagi.
If I'm right,
Jika dugaanku benar,
Sun Shitao
Sun Shitao
is probably doomed by now.
Mungkin sudah pasti gagal sekarang.
Dead or alive,
Hidup atau mati,
as long as we find him,
asalkan kita menemukannya,
they won't be able to bury this so easily.
Mereka tidak akan bisa mengubur ini semudah itu.
Then,
Kemudian,
you'll have grounds to seek justice
Anda akan memiliki dasar untuk mencari keadilan.
in Shuntian Prefecture.
di Prefektur Shuntian.
So next, your job is
Jadi selanjutnya, tugasmu adalah
to do whatever it takes
untuk melakukan apa pun yang diperlukan
to stall this case.
untuk mengulur waktu kasus ini.
The longer you drag it out,
Semakin lama Anda mengulur-ulur waktu,
the more room we'll have to maneuver.
dengan begitu kita akan memiliki lebih banyak ruang untuk bermanuver.
Got it.
Mengerti.
But,
Tetapi,
you're Lord Chief Councilor's man.
Kau adalah orang kepercayaan Ketua Dewan Agung.
Telling me all this,
Menceritakan semua ini padaku,
won't that put you in danger?
Bukankah itu akan membahayakanmu?
In this scheme,
Dalam skema ini,
I'm just the pawn.
Aku hanyalah pion.
Once the case breaks,
Begitu kasusnya terungkap,
prison will be the least of it.
Penjara akan menjadi hal terkecil yang akan Anda alami.
So doing this
Jadi melakukan ini
isn't just saving yourself,
Ini bukan hanya tentang menyelamatkan diri sendiri,
it's saving me too.
Ini juga menyelamatkan saya.
When the time comes,
Saat waktunya tiba,
if I'm locked up,
jika aku dipenjara,
I'll be counting on you.
Aku akan mengandalkanmu.
Before I left Pingyang Prefecture,
Sebelum saya meninggalkan Prefektur Pingyang,
there was only one day
hanya ada satu hari
of light rain.
hujan ringan.
Barely a drop in the bucket.
Hampir tidak ada apa-apanya.
I heard
saya dengar
the Provincial Bureau already asked the capital for aid.
Kantor Provinsi sudah meminta bantuan dari ibu kota.
The relief grain
Butir-butir bantuan
should arrive soon.
Seharusnya segera tiba.
I suppose
Kurasa begitu
it's nothing serious.
Ini bukan sesuatu yang serius.
The refugees must be fed,
Para pengungsi harus diberi makan,
that's what matters most.
Itulah yang terpenting.
If Pingyang Prefecture falls into chaos,
Jika Prefektur Pingyang jatuh ke dalam kekacauan,
then you and I,
lalu kau dan aku,
whether we beat the drum for justice
apakah kita menabuh genderang untuk keadilan
or cry bloody murder,
atau berteriak histeris,
none of it will help, we're doomed.
Semua itu tidak akan membantu, kita sudah pasti celaka.
How much grain
Berapa banyak biji-bijian?
do we have stored in Pingyang Prefecture?
Apakah kita memiliki gudang di Prefektur Pingyang?
After you told me to buy grain,
Setelah kamu menyuruhku membeli gandum,
I bought two batches right away.
Saya langsung membeli dua paket sekaligus.
About 3,500 kg total.
Totalnya sekitar 3.500 kg.
Then when the drought got worse,
Kemudian ketika kekeringan semakin parah,
I spent more silver
Saya menghabiskan lebih banyak perak
and gathered another thousand or so.
dan mengumpulkan sekitar seribu orang lagi.
Altogether,
Sama sekali,
we have around 5,000 kg.
Kami memiliki sekitar 5.000 kg.
5,000 kg…
5.000 kg…
That's still not enough.
Itu masih belum cukup.
Go to Shaanxi and Henan,
Pergilah ke Shaanxi dan Henan,
and Jiangnan too.
dan Jiangnan juga.
Even if it costs more,
Meskipun biayanya lebih mahal,
buy it all back,
beli semuanya kembali,
as much as you can.
sebisa mungkin.
If the relief grain goes wrong,
Jika pengiriman bantuan pangan gagal,
we'll step in
kita akan turun tangan
and help the government feed them.
dan membantu pemerintah memberi mereka makan.
Get the soup kitchens
Hubungi dapur umum
and medicine ready too.
dan obatnya juga sudah siap.
Miss,
Merindukan,
what's wrong?
Ada apa?
How did you know
Bagaimana kamu tahu?
something would go wrong with the relief grain?
Apakah ada yang salah dengan butiran bantuan tersebut?
Don't ask.
Jangan tanya.
All you need to know is
Yang perlu Anda ketahui hanyalah...
this is a matter of life and death.
Ini adalah masalah hidup dan mati.
We must not let the famine victims
Kita tidak boleh membiarkan para korban kelaparan
in Pingyang Prefecture
di Prefektur Pingyang
rise up in revolt.
Bangkitlah dalam pemberontakan.
So,
Jadi,
take 50,000 taels of silver
ambil 50.000 tael perak
and make another trip to Shanxi.
dan melakukan perjalanan lagi ke Shanxi.
Yes.
Ya.
Chen Yanyun, answer me,
Chen Yanyun, jawab aku.
where did the grain go?
Ke mana perginya biji-bijian itu?
Where did it go?
Ke mana perginya?
Lord Fan! Lord Fan.
Tuan Fan! Tuan Fan.
Lord Fan,
Tuan Fan,
there's no need for this.
Tidak perlu melakukan ini.
Lord Chief Councilor is not here today.
Ketua Dewan Agung tidak hadir hari ini.
Please calm down.
Tenanglah.
Alright?
Baiklah?
Lord Fan, that's not quite fair.
Tuan Fan, itu tidak adil.
For something this big,
Untuk sesuatu sebesar ini,
of course Yanyun wouldn't know.
Tentu saja Yanyun tidak akan tahu.
He's in charge of the Ministry of Revenue.
Dia bertanggung jawab atas Kementerian Pendapatan.
If he knew, what would that make him?
Jika dia tahu, lalu apa jadinya dia?
He can't exactly admit he ordered
Dia tidak mungkin mengakui secara pasti bahwa dia yang memesan.
the relief grain
biji-bijian bantuan
replaced with bran, can he?
Bisakah dia diganti dengan dedak?
Whether he ordered it or not
Entah dia yang memesannya atau tidak.
will be clear with a single investigation.
akan menjadi jelas hanya dengan satu kali penyelidikan.
Chen Yanyun,
Chen Yanyun,
you can't escape responsibility for this.
Anda tidak bisa lepas dari tanggung jawab atas hal ini.
If it leads to a riot,
Jika hal itu berujung pada kerusuhan,
you won't be able to atone even in death!
Kamu tidak akan bisa menebus kesalahanmu bahkan setelah mati!
Lord Fan, you're right.
Tuan Fan, Anda benar.
This is a major case.
Ini adalah kasus besar.
It must go through a joint trial by the Three Judicial Departments.
Kasus ini harus melalui persidangan bersama oleh Tiga Departemen Kehakiman.
At that time,
Pada saat itu,
I will also have to be questioned.
Saya juga harus diinterogasi.
This is my resignation letter.
Ini surat pengunduran diri saya.
Please, Lord He,
Ya Tuhan , kumohon ,
pass it to Lord Chief Councilor for me.
Sampaikan ini kepada Ketua Dewan Agung untuk saya.
Yanyun, you…
Yanyun, kamu…
Alright.
Baiklah.
You…
Anda…
So you were prepared all along.
Jadi, kamu sudah siap sejak awal.
And you still claim you knew nothing?
Dan kamu masih mengaku tidak tahu apa-apa?
This is a memorial I just drafted.
Ini adalah draf pidato peringatan yang baru saja saya buat.
Lord He,
Tuhan Dia,
please pass it to Lord Chief Councilor as well.
Tolong sampaikan juga kepada Ketua Dewan Agung.
You…
Anda…
You're trying to impeach Lord Fan?
Anda mencoba memakzulkan Lord Fan?
What?
Apa?
Impeach me for what?
Pemakzulan saya karena apa?
I impeach you
Saya memakzulkan Anda
for promoting your wife's brother,
untuk mempromosikan saudara laki-laki istrimu,
Zhao Jichang, the Shanxi Provincial Governor
Zhao Jichang, Gubernur Provinsi Shanxi
and for shielding his illegal acts
dan untuk melindungi tindakan ilegalnya
with your position.
dengan posisi Anda.
A total of ten charges.
Total ada sepuluh dakwaan.
Very well, Chen Yanyun.
Baik sekali, Chen Yanyun.
So this is your scheme,
Jadi, inilah rencana Anda,
isn't it?
Bukankah begitu?
You set Zhao Jichang up first,
Kamu menjebak Zhao Jichang duluan,
then impeach me.
lalu makzulkan saya.
So I'd be forced to resign in disgrace
Jadi saya akan terpaksa mengundurkan diri dengan memalukan.
and step out of the Grand Secretariat!
dan keluarlah dari Sekretariat Agung!
Right?
Benar?
Did Fu Hailian know about this?
Apakah Fu Hailian mengetahui hal ini?
He knew, didn't he?
Dia tahu, kan?
That's why he deliberately called in sick today.
Itulah mengapa dia sengaja izin sakit hari ini.
Right?
Benar?
I'll
Sakit
take my leave.
Saya pamit.
You…
Anda…
Lord Zhang, out on assignment?
Tuan Zhang, sedang menjalankan tugas?
There's a severe drought in Pingyang Prefecture.
Terjadi kekeringan parah di Prefektur Pingyang.
But the court's 200,000 kg of relief grain
Namun, bantuan gandum sebanyak 200.000 kg dari pengadilan
has somehow turned into bran.
Entah bagaimana telah berubah menjadi dedak.
Chiliarch Ye,
Chiliarch Ye,
I remember your elder sister married into
Saya ingat kakak perempuanmu menikah dengan seseorang.
the Gu family of Daxin, right?
Keluarga Gu dari Daxin, kan?
Why don't you,
Kenapa tidak kamu saja,
since you're familiar with them,
Karena kamu sudah familiar dengan mereka,
make the trip yourself?
Apakah Anda melakukan perjalanan sendiri?
Fine.
Bagus.
Not just
Tidak hanya
Gu Dezhao, the Grain Storage Director of the Ministry of Revenue,
Gu Dezhao, Direktur Penyimpanan Biji-bijian Kementerian Pendapatan,
every male member
setiap anggota laki-laki
of the Gu Manor,
dari Gu Manor,
bring them all back.
bawa mereka semua kembali.
You're abusing your power for personal revenge.
Anda menyalahgunakan kekuasaan Anda untuk balas dendam pribadi.
This is on Lord Chief Councilor's orders.
Ini atas perintah Ketua Dewan Agung.
Don't believe it? Go ask him.
Tidak percaya? Tanyakan saja padanya.
Jinzhao!
Jinzhao!
Ye Xian brought the Criminal Investigation Bureau guards
Ye Xian membawa para penjaga dari Biro Investigasi Kriminal.
to arrest people. They're even coming for Jinrong!
untuk menangkap orang-orang. Mereka bahkan datang untuk Jinrong!
Go,
Pergi,
go check the front courtyard!
Pergilah periksa halaman depan!
I really don't know what's going on!
Aku benar-benar tidak tahu apa yang sedang terjadi!
I've been wronged!
Aku telah diperlakukan tidak adil!
Young Lord,
Tuan Muda,
please speak to higher-ups for me!
Tolong sampaikan hal ini kepada atasan saya!
What does this have to do with our Censorate?
Apa hubungannya ini dengan Lembaga Sensor kita?
Why am I being charged
Mengapa saya dikenakan biaya?
along with everyone else?
bersama dengan yang lainnya?
And why are even
Dan mengapa bahkan
all the Gu men implicated?
Apakah semua pria Gu terlibat?
Take them away.
Singkirkan mereka.
Move! Young Lord!
Bergerak! Tuan Muda!
- Young Lord!
- Tuan Muda!
Move!
Bergerak!
You can't do this!
Kamu tidak bisa melakukan ini!
- This is unjust! - Young Lord!
- Ini tidak adil! - Tuan Muda!
- Uncle!
- Paman!
Uncle, why are you arresting me?
Paman, mengapa Paman menangkap saya?
- What on earth - Jinzhao! is going on?
- Apa-apaan ini - Jinzhao! yang sedang terjadi?
Jinzhao!
Jinzhao!
Save me, Jinzhao!
Selamatkan aku, Jinzhao!
The decree says detain for trial,
Dekret tersebut menyatakan untuk menahan dan mengadili,
meaning the case hasn't been fully investigated.
artinya kasus tersebut belum diselidiki secara menyeluruh.
You're totally innocent.
Kamu sama sekali tidak bersalah.
Once you're in prison,
Begitu Anda berada di penjara,
eat and sleep as usual.
Makan dan tidur seperti biasa.
Don't take anything to heart.
Jangan diambil hati.
Take care of yourselves.
Jaga diri kalian baik-baik.
Come closer.
Mendekatlah.
Make way.
Beri jalan.
What's going on?
Apa yang sedang terjadi?
This time even Jinxian and Jinrong are arrested.
Kali ini bahkan Jinxian dan Jinrong pun ditangkap.
The decree only ordered the arrest of your father.
Dekret itu hanya memerintahkan penangkapan ayahmu.
That bastard Zhang Ling is taking revenge.
Bajingan Zhang Ling itu sedang membalas dendam.
Got it.
Mengerti.
I've already arranged things in the prison.
Saya sudah mengatur semuanya di penjara.
Don't worry.
Jangan khawatir.
Take care
Hati-hati
of yourself too.
Termasuk dirimu sendiri juga.
Have they all been brought in?
Apakah mereka semua sudah dibawa masuk?
My lord, they've all been brought.
Tuanku, mereka semua telah dibawa.
Jinxian!
Jinxian!
Mother!
Ibu!
Mother, save me! Let's go.
Ibu, selamatkan aku! Ayo pergi.
Yes.
Ya.
Mother! Jinxian!
Ibu! Jinxian!
Ye Xian!
Kamu Xian!
Mother! Release Jinxian!
Ibu! Lepaskan Jinxian!
He's your own nephew!
Dia keponakanmu sendiri!
Ye Xian!
Kamu Xian!
- Auntie. - Ye…
- Bibi. - Kamu…
Lord Xian is just following orders.
Tuan Xian hanya mengikuti perintah.
Too many eyes are watching.
Terlalu banyak mata yang mengawasi.
Don't worry,
Jangan khawatir,
as long as Lord Ye is here,
selama Lord Ye masih ada di sini,
Jinxian won't suffer.
Jinxian tidak akan menderita.
You're right.
Kamu benar.
Jinzhao.
Jinzhao.
I was wrong
Aku salah
to pressure you before.
untuk menekanmu sebelumnya.
You can speak to Lord Chen,
Anda bisa berbicara dengan Tuan Chen,
please beg him
mohon padanya
to save us.
untuk menyelamatkan kita.
Grandmother,
Nenek,
it's not that I won't beg Mr. Chen.
Bukan berarti aku tidak akan memohon kepada Tuan Chen.
It's just this time,
Hanya kali ini saja,
even he may not be able to intervene.
bahkan dia mungkin tidak bisa ikut campur.
There's a problem with the disaster relief grain.
Ada masalah dengan bantuan pangan untuk penanggulangan bencana.
He's in charge of the Ministry of Revenue,
Dia bertanggung jawab atas Kementerian Pendapatan,
he'll be questioned by the Three Judicial Departments himself.
Dia akan diinterogasi langsung oleh Tiga Departemen Kehakiman.
He might even end up in jail.
Dia bahkan mungkin berakhir di penjara.
- What do we do? - Mother.
- Apa yang harus kita lakukan? - Ibu.
What do we do?
Apa yang harus kita lakukan?
All the men of our household
Semua laki-laki di rumah tangga kami
have been taken away.
telah diambil.
What do we do?
Apa yang harus kita lakukan?
Grandmother,
Nenek,
it's not completely hopeless.
Ini belum sepenuhnya tanpa harapan.
The master's private seal,
Segel pribadi sang kapten,
all his correspondence,
semua surat-menyuratnya,
and the account books,
dan buku-buku akuntansi,
bring them all out.
Keluarkan semuanya.
Don't miss a single one, be careful.
Jangan sampai terlewat satu pun, berhati-hatilah.
Got it.
Mengerti.
Miss, take a look at this.
Nona, lihat ini.
Lord Chen,
Tuan Chen,
I'm asking you,
Aku bertanya padamu,
do you know why the 200,000 kg of relief grain
Apakah Anda tahu mengapa 200.000 kg beras bantuan itu diberikan?
ended up as bran?
Berakhir menjadi dedak?
I don't know.
Aku tidak tahu.
All grain storage and release
Seluruh penyimpanan dan pelepasan biji-bijian
must go through multiple approvals in the Ministry of Revenue.
harus melalui beberapa persetujuan di Kementerian Pendapatan.
As Vice Minister of Revenue,
Sebagai Wakil Menteri Pendapatan,
in charge of the Ministry,
bertanggung jawab atas Kementerian,
how could you not know?
Bagaimana mungkin kamu tidak tahu?
It was my negligence,
Itu adalah kelalaian saya,
I didn't know the grain was switched.
Saya tidak tahu kalau jenis biji-bijiannya diganti.
Your negligence?
Kelalaian Anda?
Both of these documents
Kedua dokumen ini
were approved by you
telah disetujui oleh Anda
half a month ago.
setengah bulan yang lalu.
This grain-replacement document
Dokumen pengganti biji-bijian ini
claims that the old grain is piling up
klaim bahwa biji-bijian lama menumpuk
and may spoil,
dan mungkin akan rusak,
which would be unfavorable for public needs and state funds,
yang akan merugikan kebutuhan publik dan dana negara,
so it requests replacing it with fresh grain.
jadi, mereka meminta agar biji-bijian tersebut diganti dengan biji-bijian segar.
Whereas the replacement order and the allocation order
Sedangkan urutan penggantian dan urutan alokasi
are only three days apart.
hanya berjarak tiga hari.
On this,
Mengenai hal ini,
what's your explanation?
Apa penjelasanmu?
Jinzhao, this letter
Jinzhao, surat ini
mentions Sun Shitao.
Sun Shitao disebutkan.
In the 35th year of Jingning,
Pada tahun ke-35 pemerintahan Jingning,
he sought a promotion
Dia menginginkan promosi.
but was stopped by Father.
tetapi dihentikan oleh Ayah.
So he poured tea
Jadi dia menuangkan teh.
onto the memorial Father had written.
ke atas tugu peringatan yang telah ditulis Ayah.
Looks like old grudges.
Sepertinya ini dendam lama.
This is useful, keep it.
Ini bermanfaat, simpanlah.
Okay.
Oke.
Lord Chen,
Tuan Chen,
tell me, in the Ministry of Revenue,
Katakan padaku, di Kementerian Pendapatan,
who has such ability
yang memiliki kemampuan seperti itu
to manage so many people and matters
untuk mengelola begitu banyak orang dan berbagai hal
without being discovered?
tanpa ketahuan?
Lord Chen,
Tuan Chen,
why so silent?
Mengapa begitu diam?
I…
SAYA…
have nothing to say.
Tidak ada yang ingin kukatakan.
Lord Chen,
Tuan Chen,
you're a high-ranking court official,
Anda adalah seorang pejabat pengadilan berpangkat tinggi,
but this case is too serious,
tetapi kasus ini terlalu serius,
and you still say nothing.
dan kamu tetap tidak mengatakan apa-apa.
Then I
Lalu aku
can only ask you
hanya bisa bertanya padamu
to go to the prison at the Criminal Investigation Bureau
untuk pergi ke penjara di Biro Investigasi Kriminal
and stay there for a few days.
dan tinggal di sana selama beberapa hari.
Lord Yao,
Tuan Yao,
just follow the rules.
Ikuti saja aturannya.
Well?
Dengan baik?
Did you find out?
Apakah kamu sudah mengetahuinya?
How is Mr. Chen?
Apa kabar Pak Chen?
He's been thrown into the prison at the Criminal Investigation Bureau.
Dia telah dimasukkan ke dalam penjara di Biro Investigasi Kriminal.
They say he admitted negligence.
Mereka mengatakan dia mengakui kelalaian.
The joint trial
Percobaan bersama
ended in one hour.
berakhir dalam satu jam.
[In this game, I'm just a pawn.]
[Dalam permainan ini, aku hanyalah pion.]
[Once the case breaks,]
[Setelah kasusnya terungkap,]
[prison will be the least of it.]
[Penjara akan menjadi hal terkecil yang akan terjadi.]
Jinzhao.
Jinzhao.
Jinzhao?
Jinzhao?
I'm fine.
Saya baik-baik saja.
He took
Dia mengambil
everything on himself.
semuanya bergantung pada dirinya sendiri.
Yes.
Ya.
Also,
Juga,
I found a lead on Sun Shitao.
Saya menemukan petunjuk tentang Sun Shitao.
I didn't expect
Aku tidak menyangka
Yanyun
Yanyun
didn't even defend himself.
Dia bahkan tidak membela diri.
He just said it was his negligence
Dia hanya mengatakan itu adalah kelalaiannya.
and took all the blame.
dan menanggung semua kesalahan.
He didn't defend,
Dia tidak membela diri,
not because he didn't want to,
bukan karena dia tidak mau,
but because
tetapi karena
he saw through your plan
Dia mengetahui rencanamu.
and didn't call it out.
dan tidak mengungkapkannya.
He knew the plan
Dia tahu rencananya.
was with your tacit approval, right?
Itu dengan persetujuan diam-diammu, kan?
Yes.
Ya.
Yanyun is smart.
Yanyun itu pintar.
But I also left clues on purpose.
Tapi saya juga sengaja meninggalkan petunjuk.
So he'd cooperate, right?
Jadi dia akan bekerja sama, kan?
You think I didn't know?
Kau pikir aku tidak tahu?
You deliberately
Anda dengan sengaja
didn't tell him.
tidak memberitahunya.
My lord,
Tuanku,
I had no choice.
Saya tidak punya pilihan.
Such a big deal,
Ini masalah besar,
the fewer people who knew at the start, the better.
Semakin sedikit orang yang tahu sejak awal, semakin baik.
Besides,
Di samping itu,
Yanyun
Yanyun
seems gentle on the surface,
tampak lembut di permukaan,
but he's actually quite proud.
Tapi sebenarnya dia cukup bangga.
I was worried he wouldn't agree
Saya khawatir dia tidak akan setuju.
and might ruin things.
dan bisa merusak segalanya.
Enough.
Cukup.
Don't talk about this anymore.
Jangan bicarakan ini lagi.
When he gets out of prison,
Saat dia keluar dari penjara,
I'll smooth things over
Aku akan meredakan situasi ini.
between you two.
di antara kalian berdua.
How is Fan Chuan?
Apa kabar Fan Chuan?
He's ill.
Dia sakit.
He collapsed as soon as he got home that day.
Dia langsung pingsan begitu sampai di rumah hari itu.
Last night he heard Zhao Jichang
Tadi malam dia mendengar Zhao Jichang
was found guilty of corruption and fraud
dinyatakan bersalah atas korupsi dan penipuan
and other crimes like selling state grain
dan kejahatan lainnya seperti menjual gandum milik negara
and was ordered arrested and sent back to the capital.
dan diperintahkan untuk ditangkap dan dikembalikan ke ibu kota.
He collapsed right away.
Dia langsung pingsan.
I'm thinking
Saya sedang berpikir
we can have Han Song, Wang Chuyi
Kita bisa mendapatkan Han Song, Wang Chuyi
those censors
para sensor itu
start an impeachment.
memulai proses pemakzulan.
While he's down,
Saat dia sedang terpuruk,
finish him off.
Habisi dia.
My lord,
Tuanku,
the Prefect of Shuntian
Prefek Shuntian
just sent word
baru saja mengirim pesan
saying
pepatah
the daughter of the Director of the Ministry of Revenue
putri dari Direktur Kementerian Pendapatan
filed a petition
mengajukan petisi
to the Shuntian Prefecture.
ke Prefektur Shuntian.
She said Director Gu
Dia mengatakan Direktur Gu
was framed
dijebak
and she wanted justice for her father.
dan dia menginginkan keadilan untuk ayahnya.
Which Director Gu?
Sutradara Gu yang mana?
The Grain Storage Director of the Ministry of Revenue,
Direktur Penyimpanan Biji-bijian Kementerian Pendapatan,
Gu Dezhao.
Gu Dezhao.
The one who signed off on grain distribution.
Orang yang menyetujui distribusi biji-bijian.
His daughter…
Putrinya…
The one
Yang satu
who competed with Yanyun
yang berkompetisi dengan Yanyun
in archery and riding at the spring outing?
dalam panahan dan berkuda di acara rekreasi musim semi?
Yes, that should be her.
Ya, itu seharusnya dia.